Hello and welcome to this video in which
we'll look at the factors to be considered
when selecting a work area for an activity.
So how do you choose where
to set up a work activity?
Is it just where's most convenient, sufficient
space, or where the mess won't get in the way?
Do you think about what's needed for
the activity and create the space
specifically with this in mind?
This video will look at why it's important
that the area selected for a work activity
should be carefully chosen and what
to consider when making your decision.
We will look at health and safety, cleanliness,
product quality, accessibility, and noise
levels and environmental conditions.
Perhaps the most important factor to consider
when selecting a work area is safety.
The area should be free from hazards
that could cause injury or damage.
The work area should have adequate lighting,
ventilation, and access to emergency exits.
Consider whether the area has any flammable
materials, toxic substances, or electrical
hazards that could put the workers at risk.
Are items that are needed stored
safely, but easy to reach?
Do any of them need special storage
due to their hazardous nature?
Is there room for additional safety equipment
if needed such as fire extinguishers?
It's important that all work areas can
be kept clean as this reduces the risk of
contamination and bacterial infection, which
is part of the Health and Safety at Work
Act 1974, which we looked at in Unit 1.
When considering where a work activity
should take place, you should think
about how easy it is to be cleaned.
Can work surfaces be cleared for
cleaning and are bins nearby?
Also think about how workers will access bathrooms
and kitchen facilities, and how close these
should be, which will depend on the work involved.
Some activities aren't suitable to drink
or snack on the job, so in this case can
workers easily access another area where
they can make a drink or eat a snack.
Accessibility is also an important factor
to consider when selecting a work area.
You should choose a location that is
easily accessible by the workers and
the materials needed for the activity.
Also, consider whether there are any restrictions
on access to the area, such as during
certain times of the day or on specific days.
Think about how many people may
need access at any given time.
Is there space for them all?
Can you make the space fully accessible for
anyone using aids, such as a wheelchair?
The noise level of the work area is also
an important factor to consider that
some activities can produce a lot of
noise which can be distracting or even
harmful to the hearing of the workers.
It's important to assess the noise level and take
measures to reduce it if necessary, such as using
earplugs, ear masks or sound absorbing materials.
Conversely, does the area allow
for everyone to hear what's needed?
Many customer areas now have
hearing loop facilities installed.
Will your work area need this?
Do you have a quiet area where discussions
can take place without the need
shout over loud machinery or people?
The environmental conditions of
the work area are also important.
You should consider factors such as
temperature, humidity, and air quality.
Some activities require specific
environmental conditions to function
properly, so it's important to choose a
work area that meets these requirements.
Lighting is important for all tasks.
If there's natural light in the area, is
the workstation placed in the correct place?
For example, think about DSE guidance for where
a monitor should be placed with a nearby window.
If there's no natural light, is the lighting
installed correct for the work activity?
Product quality will differ greatly depending
on the product you are producing in your area.
For example, is the area making
a small part of a bigger item?
Is it seating for laptop users
or an area to meet with clients?
Whatever the reason, when setting up your
work activity, it is important that you
consider the product or service quality and
that the space is suitable for its needs.
For example, if it's meeting with clients,
being on the top floor of a high building
with no lift may not be the best place.
If it's producing an item,
there is more to consider.
It's no use having a state of the art setup
if the position of the work activity makes
it difficult for workers to use the necessary
machinery and link in with other production needs.
Everything we've considered in this video leads
to the production of quality products or services.
Without this the customer won't be
satisfied and you've wasted time and effort.
In conclusion, we can see that it's
not just a case of setting up a work
activity in whatever space is available.
We've highlighted just a few considerations
in this video which really shows, if you want
the space to be optimized, usable and deliver
quality, there are many factors to consider.